When did this this last trade sort of I
mean how far out did could you guys sort
of start talking with the 49ers about
you know hey this you know this
possibility
>> um the way Andrew operates in those
situation is we we start pretty early at
a variety of of possibilities and at
some point he's like hey from this pick
down let's start making calls let's
start checking in um to kind of see
what's out there and then as you get
closer to the pick things warmed up with
San Francisco and he was able to to
close the deal and um allow us to pick a
really good player in person.
>> I think I think this is only the third
time that Andrew has traded up to select
a player, you know, he's usually going
to trade back and collect assets. What
is it about Emanuel's um skill set that
made it so appealing and I know he even
mentioned a week ago about positionless
hybrid defenders and those big nickel
packages?
>> Yeah, I think it in this case like we're
trying to build a team here. Um, it's
not just always about adding assets or
collecting picks. Um, when there's a
player that's still on your board that's
falling to you that you have, you know,
really high grades on both as a person,
as a player, um, it becomes a no-brainer
when when you have an opportunity.
That's really how we felt about Eman.
>> Do you guys consider him kind of a
center fielder, free safety, ball hawk
type safety? Yeah, we really see him as
a versatile player that's going to be
able to play at a variety of spots for
us. Uh to what you just said, Ball Hawk
is definitely in in the description. Um
and really just someone that with his
size, his athleticism, the way he moves
for his size. Um I was down at his pro
day and uh it's pretty impressive. So I
think really someone that's going to be
able to give us options.
>> Other than his pro day, what were the
interactions with Amino through this? He
was here too for uh for a top 30 visit.
Uh just a really mature, impressive
young man. Talked about uh when we met,
he talked about his journey. Um not
having a lot of offers coming out of
high school going to Jo and then how he
felt uh the connection the chemist the
chemistry sorry at Toledo when he went
there. They offered him he committed on
the spot. Um and then he had offers to
transfer uh decided to stay which as you
guys all know it's almost I think a
something pretty rare nowadays. Um just
was really loyal to the school that gave
him a chance and he wanted to um do the
best he could there and he did that. So
really we're welcoming someone that's
going to really add to our culture um
and someone that's extremely extremely
um mature and wellrounded. Yeah, I know
you guys game g game try and game
everything out, you know, going into the
draft, but considering the four players
that you were able to end up with, uh it
almost feels like you couldn't have game
that out if you if you tried. Just what
how pleasant of a surprise was it for
you guys to be able to, you know, get
these four players and um you know,
economize your your picks while doing
it? Yeah, I think uh to your point
there's a in the draft there's a mix of
skill and luck and I think we're um
some of this is coming together this
year in terms of how the plays how the
picks sorry have played out and we've
just been able to acquire some really
good players at every spot so far. Um
and again that will be additive both on
and off the field. Kevin, you now have
four picks in the fifth round. I believe
first year you guys have had multiple
picks in the fifth round. Does Andrew
consider that some kind of magic route
or something or what? Just coincidence.
You guys keep collecting fish?
>> Uh definitely no magic, but I'd say like
those assets can be valuable whether
that's for um coming back up, packing
packaging them to come back up. Um those
are we really can use them in a variety
of ways. Um and and if not, make the
picks. Uh there's some good players that
come out of the fifth round as well, and
that can be great additions for our
team. So, at this point, uh we just want
to continue to improve our team and and
get the best players we can.
>> Just from a skill set standpoint, uh can
you just kind of run through what is so
special about Emanuel?
>> I think what's so special about Emanuel
is the versatility that he brings. Um
you're thinking of a player that can
play high, can play low. um a player
that have excellent ball skills, um
size, strength, physicality. So really a
player that the way we want to play
defense just gives our defensive coaches
so many options. Um and I think they're
going to be extremely I I don't think I
know they're going to be extremely
pleased to work with him.
>> Yeah. Which seems like he's so good at
that. Peanut punch in particular and
forcing fumbles. Like what do you guys
see from him on film with with that
aspect? just like the physicality to
your point like um two things that
Andrew harp on us all the time is to
bring guys here in this building that
are tough and competitive and he he
embodies that uh the way he plays is
exactly the type of football um that we
want to play and he'll continue to do
that here at our level. How important is
that versatility when you guys play as
much three safety packages as you do?
>> I think I think it's huge and again like
um the defensive coaches will obviously
figure out how to best use them in and
in in different scenarios but again I
cannot emphasize the versatility
versatility point more just in terms of
option that it gives to to our coaches
to deploy him and maximize his
strengths. when you mentioned uh you're
almost surprised that he decided to stay
at Toledo when he could have gone
elsewhere. How do you gauge a a person's
players personality when it seems like
they'll jump at the uh
from year to year at the transfer
program?
>> Yeah, it's a good question. I think like
overall everybody makes their own
decision, you know, whether that's
that's
their own reasons, their personal
reasons. So, it's not really a matter of
judging whether you're transferring or
not. It's more a matter of giving him
the credit to staying loyal to the
school and really wanted to uh give back
to the school that gave him a chance uh
when he didn't really have any offers
now that he was producing and he could
have just uh left. And he said something
to me that really stuck out. he said
something along the lines of, you know,
the long-term financials or the big, you
know, uh, financial gains will come when
I make it to the NFL. And that's kind of
was his mindset. So, just it's just a
testament to him and his maturity and
his process and all that.
>> It's obviously not a secret like not all
college programs are created equal.
There's the FBS, the FCS, whatever. the
the MAC schools aren't considered like
the premier programs, but you know,
back-to-back years now where you took
you're taking Emanuel McNeel Warren at
Toledo, obviously Harold Fannon last
year. How what what are the things that
you like see or can can use to know like
this isn't just a guy who's doing it in
the MAC or at a smaller level. This is a
guy that we know can play with the other
players in the in the higher up leagues
or in the NFL and actually make it. Um,
I like that you asked that question
because that's a conversation we had uh
a lot when I was working in Philly uh
under obviously Howie Roseman and Tom
Dono who'd been a GM obviously been in
the league for a long time and when we
talk about level competition of course
you have to take it into account in your
in your eval evaluation process but he'd
say they play against who they got to
play and at some point that's what we
need to evaluate and that's our job to
project that based on the tools that
they have their athletic profile and how
We think that's going to project again
against against NFL talent. And at every
level, it is a projection. Now, maybe
easier to make in some programs than
others, but that's our job and that's
that's what we um spend a ton of time
doing watching the tape. Um but at the
end of the day, who they play against as
a tape, we got to watch and that's our
job to project.
>> Ander had mentioned that, you know, with
that more teams playing three safety,
that position is sort of gaining in
profile. Is that position becoming more
and more important as far as like you
know obviously we always talk about edge
rushers and corners and things like that
but is safety starting to kind of reach
that level?
>> I think at the end of the day regardless
of position of course there's premium
premium position and those types of
things but at the end of the day like
any position that's going to make an
impact take the ball away from for us
like take it away uh give it back to our
offense. Those became playmakers and
that's what we're trying to add at every
position. Um, and Iman brings that.
>> The draft is part skill, part luck. How
do you improve the the skill part of it?
>> I think it goes back to your process. It
goes back to um the the the ton of film
that we watch. That's where it starts.
Um, and that's years of years of work
from our area scouts. That's really like
the ground the ground level, the
starting point. And then you add all the
other piece of information that you
gather through your process, whether
that's the medical information, your
character, your testing numbers, um the
interactions you've had with them, what
the coaches think of them. And as to me,
your process gets better as you get
better at aggregating all that
information and make good decisions,
sound decisions. Um again, good player,
good person. Uh those are things we
can't miss on.
>> This was this was a couple more. This is
a player that was projected by many
amateurs as a first round pick. Um, do
you think he fell farther than you
expected or is this the range that you
guys projected this player?
>> Uh,
we're just happy with where we took him.
I mean, where he was on our board for
us, it was a no-brainer to get up and
get him based on what we think he's
going to bring bring to our program. So,
at that point for us is just really
excited about where we got him.
>> Still point for a second. How much does
experience help just being able to go
through multiple drafts and and learn
from um how you how you've done in the
past?
>> I think it's experience. I think it's
the team that you have around yourself
that you surround yourself with. Andrew
has done an excellent job of of having a
staff that is um diverse uh in terms of
skill experience. I mean just at the
table right now upstairs we have uh Tom
Telesco and Chris Bolan. Uh you have
Jimmy Ray who's done that for decades.
So just the level of experience that we
have in advising um in advising our
decision maker is just is just diverse
and excellent. So I think that helps
that definitely helps our process and in
making good decisions when the time
comes.
Good.